Mayor's Mansion Debate Collection 129
People's Archive, MLK Library
Mayor's Mansion Debate Collection
2001-2003
People's Archive, MLK Library
Bray, Howard
129
1.67 Linear feet
4 Boxes
Arrangement
Series 1: Donating Party Series consists of materials documenting individuals who either worked with, or represented Mrs. Eugene Casey, the donor of the proposed mansion. As her legal representative, Richard Carr corresponded frequently with city officials, and authorized an appraisal of the proposed site, which was conducted by Harps and Harps, Inc. Series 2: Government Series consists of folders dedicated to the local government agencies involved in the decision-making process for the proposed mansion. Series 3: Neighborhood Groups and Committees Series consists of folders dedicated to individuals, committees, and neighborhood groups who worked closely with the city government, National Park Service, and Casey Foundation. Their goal was to determine whether the creation of the proposed mayor's mansion was in the best interests of the impacted neighborhood and community. Series 4: Public Response This series consists of folders which focus on the general public response to the proposed mayor's mansion. Materials include records of a public hearing,press documents, and correspondence).
Biographical / Historical
The Mayor's Mansion Debate Collection documents a proposed track of land which was to be donated to Washington, DC by Mrs. Eugene Casey. The donation included the stipulation that the property be designated specifically for use as the mayor's official residence. While many local residents and government officials were appreciative of the proposed gift, responses to the proposed donation remained mixed. Among the concerns raised by residents and city officials was the financing to cover costs of maintenance; issues of providing security to the property; whether the city and National Park Service should engage in a proposed land-swap; and whether moving the mayor's residence to Georgetown would create the perception of elitism. The debate over accepting the proposed gift remained undecided, and in late 2003, the Casey Foundation ultimately withdrew the offer, and donated the land to the Salvation Army. In the aftermath, Howard Bray, a local resident who was actively engaged in the debate, submitted a request for inter-office correspondence and reports through the Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) to the National Park Service, Washington City Council, and the Mayor's Office.
Custodial History
Howard Bray donated this collection, which he acquired from several government agencies and non-profit groups under the Freedom of Information Act (FOIA).
Custodial History
Howard Bray donated this collection, which he acquired from several government agencies, and non-profit groups under the aforementioned Freedom of Information Act (FOIA).
Scope and Contents
The collection consists primarily of correspondence, in the form of emails, faxes, and letters. Additional materials include: reports, testimonies, maps, copies of deeds, and appraisals from both government agencies, and private citizens.
Maps; Correspondence; Real Property; Politics and government
- Series 1: Donating Party
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of folders dedicated to individuals who either worked with or representing the donor of the proposed mansion, Mrs. Eugene Casey. As her legal representative, Richard Carr corresponded heavily with city officials and authorized an appraisal of the proposed site, which was carried out by Harps & Harps, Inc.
  - Richard Carr - Correspondence, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Richard Carr - Appraisal/maps/petition/real estate amendment, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Richard Carr - Speech, 9/4/2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Eugene B. Casey Foundation - Correspondence, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Harps and Harps - Correspondence/appraisals, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series 2: Government
  This series consists of folders dedicated to all the local government agencies involved in the decision-making process for the proposed mayor's mansion.
  - City Council - Correspondence/memorandum/reports/announcements, 1/2003-9/2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - City Council - Correspondence/reports, 10/2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Department of Transportation - Correspondence, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Executive Office of the Mayor (EOM) - Correspondence/speech notes, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Executive Office of the Mayor (EOM) - Correspondence/reports/article, 3/2003-8/2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Executive Office of the Mayor (EOM) - Correspondence/reports/press release, 9/2003-2/2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Metropolitan Police Department - Correspondence, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - National Park Service - Correspondence/reports, 1935-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - National Park Service - Correspondence/land transfer agreements/reports/webpage articles, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - National Park Service - Correspondence/reports, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - National Capital Planning Commission (NCPC) - NCPC File #6375: "Transfer of Jurisdiction of a Portion of U.S. Reservation 357" - reports/correspondence/quarterly newsletter, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Office of the Corporation Council (OCC) - Memorandum/correspondence/drafts of lease agreement/articles of incorporation and bylaws, 2000-2003 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Office of Planning (OP) - Correspondence/memorandum/contract, 9/2002-8/2003 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Office of Planning (OP) - Correspondence/memorandum/draft of contract/notes, 9/2003-12/2003 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Proposed Land Exchange Agreement - Environmental assessment, 11/2002 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series 3: Neighborhood Groups and Committees
  This series consists of folders dedicated to individuals and neighborhood groups and committees which worked closely with the city government, National Park Service, and Casey Foundation to determine Series 3: Neighborhood Groups and Committees: This series consists of folders dedicated to individuals and neighborhood groups and committees which worked closely with the city government, National Park Service, and Casey Foundation to determine whether the creation of the proposed mayor's mansion was in the best interests of the impacted neighborhood and community.
  - Advisory Neighborhood Commissions - Correspondence/reports, 2001-2003 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Biological Resource Inventory Report - Draft of report, 11/4/2002 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bray, Howard - Correspondence, court ruling, memorandum, notes (contains records related to Mr. Bray's request for information via FOIA), Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Casey Mansion Committee - Correspondence/memorandum/meeting reports/reports, 2001-3/2003 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Casey Mansion Committee - Correspondence/reports, 4/2003-10/2003 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Defenders of Wildlife - Correspondence/environmental assessment, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Foxhall Community Citizens Association - Correspondence/reports, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Foxhall Community Citizens Assocation - Correspondence/petition/reports, 1/2003-4/2003 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Foxhall Community Citizens Association, 5/2003-11/2003 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Foxhall Community Citizens Association - Newsletters/photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Friends of Whitehaven Park - List of Exhibits, Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence - Correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Report of the Mayor's Official Residence Commission - Report, April 24 2001 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series 4: Public Response
  This series consists of folders which focus on the general public response to the proposed mayor's mansion (as evidenced through a public hearing, the press, and correspondence).
  - Press (1 of 2) - Newspaper clippings/articles/editorials, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Press (2 of 2) - Newspaper clippings/articles/editorials, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Public Hearing - Testimonies, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Public Opinion - Correspondence, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Public Opinion - Correspondence, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)